A Guide to the Papers of Thomas Law, 1803-1834
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Thomas Law, 1803-1834
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
2801
This collection consists of items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Scope and Content Information
The papers contain the correspondence, 1806-1834, of Thomas Law regarding legal, business, and family matters; relations between the United States and Great Britain; the construction of the Washington Canal; the War of 1812; land values in Washington, D.C.; his loyalty to the United States; the death of Lady Rumbold; the abolition of slavery and the emancipation of slaves; economic conditions in India and the East India Company; and U.S. politics.
Topics also include discussion of the presidential election of 1828; his advocacy of a national currency; the Columbian Institute; the British economy; the Irish Question; George Long; dueling; George Henry Law; the Reform Act of 1832; the Holy Alliance; travel including trips to springs in Virginia and the University of Virginia, and economic policy in Mexico after its independence from Spain. Correspondents include Lady Rumbold, Charles Rumbold, George Henry Law, and Edmund Law, Thomas Law's son.
The collection also includes a letter, 28 May 1829, from Henry Clay, Lexington, Ky., to Thomas Law, regarding a land title case in Kentucky, U.S. politics, and Andrew Jackson.
The papers also contain miscellaneous Law family correspondence, 1803-1824, regarding the French Revolution, relations between the United States and Great Britain, the War of 1812, Thomas Law, and Washington D.C. Included is a handwritten copy of a letter, 5 July 1824, from James Monroe to Richard Rush, regarding Thomas Law. Other correspondents include John Law, Thomas Percy, and Edmund Law Lushington.
Contents List
- John Law, Bishop of Elphim, to the Lord Bishop of Dromore [T. Percy] (Elphin to Dromore) 1803 Mar 23, 2p w/addr
  " ... My brother Tom (the American) is in Paris. He would not stay if there were much danger of war .... "
- H[arriet] and E[lizabeth]; R[umbold] to their brother, Charles Rumbold 1803, 3p w/addr
  " ... the last time Mama heard from my Uncle Tom he was very well, very much pleased with Paris he has been presented to Buonoparte though he did [not] wish it ... "
- Thomas Law to Mr. Elliot seeks aid in recovering payment from Mr. Atkinson 1806 Mar 22, 1p w/addr
- Edmund Law to his sister, Lady Rumbold (Isle of Thanet to Southhampton) mentions Thomas Law's preparations to go to America and his property in America 1806 Sep 7, 3p w/addr
- Edmund Law to his sister, Lady Rumbold (London to Southhampton) 1808 Mar 28, 2p w/addr
  " ... Tom ... had almost determined to sail ... when a [letter] from me ... & ... the Embargo determined him to stay "
- Thomas Law to his sister, Lady Rumbold (Philadelphia to Southampton) 1811 Jul 18, 5p w/addr
  " ... This country occupies my mind & expands my heart, for wherever I go I perceive improvements, prosperity, & happiness ... I have been very busy in promoting a Canal through the City [Philadelphia] "
- Thomas Law to his sister, Lady Rumbold (Philadelphia to London) 1813 Dec 21, 3p w/addr
  " ... My lots are rising fast in value ... It is inconceivable how wealth is increasing in the United States ... Every day I lament that the war continues ... but the people will never submit to impressment ... the war is becoming more popular ... "
- Robert V. Law to his aunt, Lady Rumbold (Cheasapeake Bay to Southampton) 1814 Sep 18, 2p w/addr
  " ... you will certainly have heard of the Destruction of Washington. We have just made an unsuccessful attack upon Baltimore ... with the loss of not more than 150 men, the Yankee's being afraid of attack us ... "
- Edmund Lushington to his aunt, Lady Rumbold (Hancock, Middlesex to Southampton) 1814 Dec 27, 3p w/addr
  " ... Preliminaries of peace with America are signed ... to my Uncle Thomas [Law] individually it must be an event of the highest importance. His situation in America during the war must ... have been painful ... "
- Thomas Law to his sister, Lady Rumfold (Washington to London) 1815 Feb 18, 3p w/addr
  " ... appropriations have now been granted ... to reerect the public buildings [in Washington], & a misfortune will prove of great future benefit to me ... I pitied the noble Veterans ... sent here to whiten American coasts with their bones ... This Country will never be so unprepared again ... the burning of the library ... was most disreputable ... why was the war prolonged? The British ministers must answer this question ... "
- Thomas Law to his niece, [Maria], Lady Temple (from Philadelphia) 1815 May 15, 4p
  " ... the ruins of ... the Capitol excited painful sensations & motions to remove the seat of Govt. threatened me with ruin ... I had also a Cancery Suit ... which I apprehended would decree to me the length ... came the joyful tidings of peace & then a decree for 60,000 Dollars ... I have accomplished a favorite object ... a Canal from the Potowmac to the Eastern branch through the City & I have now a Bank ... at New Orleans ... [the Americans] were placed behind bags of Cotton three deep, the ablest marksmen in front & the other two to load the rifles - thus the front men fired about three times in a minute ... "
- Thomas Law to his sister, Lady Rumbold (Philadelphia to Southampton) 1815 Jul 5, 3p w/addr
  " ... I am about to accompany my daughter ... to Ballstown in New York ... The accomodations in these steamboats are ... superb ... my property in Washington City has risen 100 pcent ... a Canal which I suggested ... will be finished this year ... I have also effected the establishment of a Bank ... I wish you could view this happy prosperous Country ... "
- Thomas Law to his sister, [Lady Rumbold] (from Washington) 1816 Feb 1, 1p
  " ... in four or five months I shall be a wealthy man again ... There is a young lady here ... I have followed here with my eye ... with emotions I cannot describe ... "
- Thomas Law to his sister, Lady Rumbold (Philadelphia to Southampton) 1816 Oct 28, 3p w/addr
  " ... My prospects in Washington City brighten daily ... My daughter ... will I believe marry ... I regret to learn that there is so much distress in England ... The British ministry has ... rendered all the industrious productive Englishmen discontented - This country affords an asylum for the oppressed ... If a man be ruined ... he has only to go to the back Country to acquire another ... my property rises most rapidly in value ... my Sons are making fortunes ... "
- Thomas Law to his sister, Lady Rumbold (Washington to Southampton) 1817 Apr 20, 3p w/addr
  " ... My daughter Elina I gave to Mr. Rogers ... of a most respectable family ... it is pleasing to view the improvements [in Washington] ... similar progress is made throughout the United States ... I regret the poor are suffering so much in my native land ... G.B. has a surplus popul[atio]n... here 40 m[illio]n are wanted ... I have turned farmer ... let me entreat of you to purchase american funds, they will rise ... "
- [Thomas Law] to his sister, [Lady Rumbold] (from "Tusculum") 1817 Aug 20, 4p frag
  " ... When just returned from India I could not enter into your rural sensations, but now I am in possession of a country seat. I feel such pleasure from farming & gardening ... My old servant Frost is come back ... I enjoy ... prosperity after much delay & some anxiety - when my Countrymen burnt the Capitol. I wish you had secured a portion of your fortune in the american funds ... my plans in India have succeeded ... I have given Mr. Baget a financial System which will I think produce many millions and without taxation ... "
- Thomas Law to his sister, Lady Rumbold (Baltimore to Southampton) 1818 Oct 10, 2p w/addr
  " ... at my daughters, Mrs. Rogers, she has a fine boy ... My sons John & Edmund continues to rise in fame & fortune. John has two sons Edmund is not married ... I have ... felt a little rheumatism or flying gout & ... a land has escaped bankruptcy ... I amuse myself with farming & gardening & with writing now & then poetry or on finance ... & trace my disposition to promote the good of mankind to my early pursuits in India ... "
- Thomas Law to his sister, Lady Rumbold ([Washington] to Southampton) 1819 Mar 1, 2p w/addr
  " ... My poor Brothers death ... I have therefore written to my Brother George to obtain me Justice that I may return ... My Br Lord Ellenborough was too impetuous & harsh ... yet I would leave this for a while to be at Sydney Farm [Lady Rumbold's residence] ... "
- Thomas Law to his sister, Lady Rumbold (Philadelphia to Southampton) 1819 Jul 19, 3p w/addr
  " ... I am urging Elina to accompany me to see you all ... My City property is rising fast - my Canal through the City is finished ... I have established a Society similar to the one I introduced at Calcutta ... collecting & distributing the various vegetable productions of this & of other countries ... & to connect with it a cabinet of minerals ... to apply to Congress for the appropriation of ... the Mall& etc ... "
- Thomas Law to his sister, Lady Rumbold (Washington to Watton) 1819 Jul 29, 2p w/addr
  " ... I live almost entirely in the Country on a farm of 258 acres. It borders on one side on the District Line ... when a little fatigued with country concerns I go to town [to] see a play & enjoy the amusements ... It pains me to read of distress at Carlisle ... "
- Edmund Law to Charles Rumbold (Washington to London) 1823 Jul 15, 4p
  " ... you will perhaps be surprised at receiving this letter from your juvenile companion & schoolfellow ... my Father bears up against his domestic afflictions ... his constitution is strong for one at his age ... his mind still retains all the vigour & animation of youth ... Mr Blane's friends must prevail upon him to arrange for publication the numerous notes he has taken [in the United States] ... you have lost an affectionate mother..and I have lost a Brother ... "
- Thomas Law to his nephew, Charles Rumbold (from Ibbostons to Herfordshire) 1824 Oct 18, 1p w/addr
  " ... I arrived here on Sunday night after a tedious passage [from America] & encountering a hurricane off Holyhead ... my much loved Sister's death I much lamented ... It will please you to see the enclosed shewing how I parted from my friends in America ... Encloses copy of 2 letters: "
- James Monroe to Richard Rush, (U.S. Envoy Extra-[ordinary& Minister Plenepot[entiar]y)1824 Jul 5, 1p
  " ... My object in this is to add my testimony to that of his numerous friends, in this his adopted Country, to the merit of Mr Law ... that you extend to you, such kind attention ... he may have depending there ... and "
- Thomas Fingey, et al, to [Thomas Law] 1824 Jul 9, 1p
  " ... your friends in the City [of Washington] ... having been informed that it is your intention shortly to embark for England ... invite you to a public dinner at Queens hotel on Monday next ... "
- Thomas Law to [his nephew], Charles Rumbold ([Ibbotsons] to Herf[ordshire]) [1824 Nov 11], 1p w/addr
  " ... I must first go to my B[other]r the Bishop ... I have been reading all the publi[cit]y respecting Slavery-the pamphlet entitled "Immediate not gradual abolition" is ably written-but the only remedy is ... the Independence of Hayti & the emigration of enlightened people of color from the United States ... "
- Thomas Law to his nephew, Charles Rumbold (written in England to London) 1825 Apr 13, 3p w/addr
  " ... I have received very pleasant news from America - [my son] Edmund concludes " ... the liberality displayed your return ... to your adopted Country ... since your departure from India" ... By an addition I am making to my pamphlet ... I shall prove ... that famines have been averted by my System ... amongst my old papers, I find the enclosed Letter from Jefferson ... [and] One from Monroe ... I am not very well ... "
- Thomas Law to his nephew, Charles Rumbold (Horsted to London] 1825 Jul 8, 2p w/addr
  " ... I am determined to be at Liverpool [to sail for America] about the 15th ... I shall leave behind me a plan to be given to the [East India] Company ... & only regret that the Company, did not decide on my claim before my departure ... "
- [Thomas Law] to his nephew, [Charles Rumbold] (written from the United States?) [late 1825?], 4p frag
  " ... Before I left England, I expressed my apprehension of ... a run upon the banks ... these one & two pound notes amounted to 30,000,000 ... Think how the British manufacturers must have suffered when called upon by the banks to pay those notes ... The poor wretches who have destroyed power looms do not understand that the french will benefit ... I enclose you two tracts on the advantages of a National paper currency & on the disadvantages of a specie basis... the natural result of a paper currency is little fluctuation, for the quantity may be regulated as I have shewn by the demand ... shew these tracts to ... be of service to my Country [England] ... The product of american mines ... has much declined ... Those governments which allowed banks to coin small paper notes [based on specie] are now suffering ... In the United States the Banks have ruined thousands ... During the war I congratulated Mr Madison ... and proved to him that increased paper money would ... enable government to pay ... "
- [Thomas Law] to his niece, Maria [Rumbold] (wife of Sir Grenville Temple) (from Washington) 1825 Dec 12, 5p w/addr
  " ... I was last week in the Chair as the first promotor of the Columbian Institute & Mr Clay, Rush, Southward & Barbour (Heads of Departments) were proposed to be balloted for as Members ... I am to deliver an address in favor of a National paper Currency ... This will be my opus maximum - after that I shall add a Chapter to my "Instinctive moral impulses" & so close my Career. I presented an address ... desiring the body of Washington to be removed ... to the vault purposely made in the Capitol..my pamphlet on India has made a great impression ... measures have been adopted to come back to my System ... This National currency System which I now expect to establish here ... [will provide] sufficiency of currency, property will rise in value. Canals roads & railways can be made ... There is scarcely gold enough in America for wedding rings ... "
- Thomas Law to his nephew, Charles Rumbold ([Washington] to London) 1825 Dec 13, 1p w/addr
  " ... Edmund [my son] is ... aiding me to be ready for the Columbian Institute ... if I make converts of Congress, I shall be consoled for 20 years labor ... as foreigners are establishing our machinery, they will import fewer British goods. Our absentees on the Continent of Europe also drain G. B ....I hope you will receive favorable accounts from India - but unless some of the mea[sures] I recommended are adopted, peace cannot long continue ... I was pleased with Mr Rice's speech at Limerick though not by his mode of returning my "Instinctive Impulses" ... "
- Thomas Law to his nephew, Charles Rumbold ([Washington] to London) 1826 Apr 18, 1p w/addr
  " ... When in England, I gave my mind to that defective part of the East India Company ... The enclosed pamphlet, may I think be useful at this crisis in my native Country, which must suffer by a vain attempt to have a paper currency based on Specie ... Edmund [my son] as I wrote you is gone ... to Mexico ... This year an influenza ... threatens to relieve me from the troubles of life ... If I obtain Justice from the Company, I shall sell off here ... "
- Thomas Law to his nephew, Charles Rumbold ([Washington] to London) 1828 Oct 1, 3p w/addr
  " ... My stomach being deranged & my nerves affected by hot weather, I went with two friends to the several springs in Virginia ... I wanted to recover health enough to accomplish three important works ...
  1st a plan for a National Currency
  2nd [a plan] to emancipate the slaves ...
  3rd a continuation of my Essays on moral emotions ...
  on my way to [the University of Virginia at] Charlottesville ... I obtained the following narrative - The gentleman's name was [Professor George] Long & he was going with his wife to England. She has been the wife of my friend Seldens brother who was killed in a duel by a wretch in the Western Country ... Gen[eral Andrew] Jackson who is proposed for President ... murdered a Mr Dickenson in the same manner ... Must not Mrs Long love a husband so talented that he was chosen & brought from England to the University here & then invited back [to teach at the University of London] ... If I can I will cross the sea once more ... "
- Thomas Law to his nephew, Charles Rumbold (Washington to London) 1829 Mar 13, 2p w/addr
  " ... publication I submitted to the perusal of our Unitarian preacher here who as travelled through Europe ... he wrote me a note of which I enclose a copy ... What folly it is to withhold from the Roman Catholics ... One hand of G. B. is employed in keeping down the Irish ... losing the monopoly of Cotton, the french Cotton goods are preferred ... Our election for President is over, and the profanum vulgar has appointed Genl Jackson - enclosed are some lines which I scrawld ... getting ready to visit Mr Adams, Clay & Rush ... Clerks are turned adrift to make way for the turbulent Democrats ... Edmund has been very ill ...
  Enclosures: "
- copy of letter from Unitarian Minister and 1829 Feb 24, 2p
- poem, With virture, Knowledge, prudence and firm soul ... N.D., 2p
- Thomas Law to Mrs. Tucker ([Washington] to London) 1829 Jul 1, 1p w/addr
  " ... By the enclosed you will learn of my loss ... My Sister Rumbold's Love ... made her a mother to Edmund ... Her son Charles & he were great friends - pray send the enclosed to him, after letting my B[rothe]r the Bishop read them ... I have finished my [pub]lications on finance & may ben[efit] my native country ... My third part on moral principles will I hope benefit the whole human race ...
- manuscript obituary of Thomas Law's son, Edmund N.D., 3p
- Cary Selden to Thomas Law (within Washington) 1830 Apr 26, 1p
  " ... to recommend to you a suitable and fit person to act as an agent ... I take pleasure in naming Mr. James Adams of this City ... "
- Thomas Law to his nephew, Charles Rumbold (from Liverpool to Hants) 1831 Nov 2, 3p w/addr
  " ... I will preserve my health during the winter in america, & think of the Cottage & your family Church, where I shall have my mortal coil deposited ... I was so confident that the Company would not pocket, the interest of my Stock in Calcutta that I applied to no one ... had I ... obtained influential aid I might have succeeded ... the Zyots in India were driven by despair to insurrection against that monstrous atrocious system which I have been so long deprecating ... Though numbers have had honors & pensions for temporary services, no one [else has] been so instrumental in establishing a permanent good ... "
- Thomas Law to his nephew, Charles Rumbold (Washington to London) 1832 Jan 10, 3p w/addr
  " ... [my son-in-law] Rogers told me of the death of [Eliza] Custis ... she always Loved me - after our separation when I was sick, she ... insisted upon nursing [me] ... she was a beautiful young woman with a fine person[ality]& nearly related to Genl. [George] Washington ....I am come here with a great financial plan & also to do away slavery ... Shew my addresses to the Columbian Institute to Mr Stanley & Rice - read Jacobs he confirms all that I suggested ... the Govt. to make a few m[illio]n of notes for Ireland, all the men might be employed ... 49062 passengers have arrived in Canada ... I have called on one person only Mr Clay to give him extracts from Jacobs & tc & to submit my ideas to him ... You know I hate Jackson, he ran away with another man's wife - killed a worthy man in a duel ... I do not wish this to be mentioned, or Van Buren the american minister might hear of it ... "
- Thomas Law to his nephew, Charles Rumbold ([Washington] to Hants) 1832 Mar 6, 1p w/addr
  " ... I have in truth suffered much & can only hope for relief in warm weather - my friend Blane did the same ... I thought of my grandchildren & of attachments here, & could not foresee hurricanes & running on a bar, & a frost ten below Zero ... I was ... complimented in the National Intelligence & all my fellow Citizens called even those from the Country ... "
- Thomas Law to his nephew, Charles Rumbold ([Washington] to Basingstoke) 1832 Jul 17, 2p w/addr
  " ... I have been most uneasy since the rejection of the reform Bill by the House of Lords ... I am very adverse to the banking System & have written a few Essays on finance which have made a considerable impression. [President Andrew] Jackson extols them, I am however opposed ... violently to him ... Having suffered much on my voyage ... & after much puzzling have made the discovery so that by the simple magnetic needle alone the navigator can discover what longitude it is ... I will send the whole plan over to you - it is most simple as only a circular map & a needle in the centre are required ... If the government at home finds the Revenue falls short, there is a good plan to transfer part of the National Debt to India ... "
- Thomas Law to his newphew, Charles Rumbold ([Providence] to Basingstoke) [1832 Nov 7], 2p w/addr
  " ... I have been a journey of above 500 miles to see my grandchildren by my son John - their christian names are Thomas & Edmund ... The steam boat I went in from New York to Providence was 170 feet long & I sat down to a table of 100 to a very excellent dinner ... When I left Washington a servant had died in the house, a clergymen in the next room was recovering & nine had died of the Cholera within pistol shot of me in a week ... Charcoal & sweet oil they say is a certain antedote ... The sending of troops to Ireland is beneficial for money is spending among them, my plan would have prevented this ... tell Mr Barlow that I am finishing my work on moral sensations and impulses ... "
- manuscript, "Reflections" or "Rhymes on Reform" by [Thomas Law] N.D. [1832], 3p
  "I had seen corruption by its foes expos'd Yet patriot reformers strove in vain, I therefore though the System now propos'd would by the phalanx be overthrown again ... Thank Heaven this City does no mobs deplore And by results we pleas'd conclusions draw That an enlightened people shut uproar, And strength acquire as they conform to law ... "
- Thomas Law to Charles Rumbold ([Washington] to Basingstoke, Hants) 1833 Aug 18, 2p w/addr
  " ... Your generous offer [to remain in England] I might not to have refused, but ... my Brother George had much wounded my feelings by his conduct to me & I disapproved of his conduct in the House of Lords & the [East India] Company had treated me unjustly a second Time..Enclosed is a valuable plan ... give them to the President of the Board of Control & the Chancellor of the Exchequer ... The Cotton manufacture in England is receiving a rivalship here & in the South ... "
- Thomas Law to his brother, George ([Washington] to Bishopry of Bath and Wells) N.D. [1832], 3p w/addr
  " ... Your refusal to be my Security although I shewed you I had stocks ... caused me more a pain than I have ever suffered ... Your professions in your pamphlet are ridiculed here - they allude to your opposition to the Roman Catholic bill ... in short they say you expected to turn out Lord Grey & the administration & to prevent all reforms ... as you persuaded me to cross the atlantic ... pride prevented me from taking your advice to apply to Charles Rumbold ... "
- [Thomas Law] to his nephew, [Charles Rumbold] 18[34] Feb 12, 2p frag